Inventory of the Barbara J. Hazard papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Barbara J. Hazard papers
1986-2008
2015C1
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes (4.2 linear feet)
Diary entries, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and slides relating to artists in Leningrad/Saint Petersburg in the late Soviet and post-Soviet periods. Includes letters by Russian artists, photographs of their artwork, and exhibit catalogs.
Hazard, Barbara J.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
Barbara J. Hazard, born in 1931, was an American artist who was heavily involved in supporting the Tovarishchestro Eksperimental'nogo Izobrazitel'go Isskustva (Fellowship for Experimental Fine Art) with St. Petersburg artists throughout the 1980s and 1990s.
Scope and Contents note
Diary entries, correspondence, printed matter, photographs, and slides relating to artists in Leningrad/Saint Petersburg in the late Soviet and post-Soviet periods. Includes letters by Russian artists, photographs of their artwork, and exhibit catalogs.
Art --Russia (Federation); Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Slides (Photography).
- Leningrad Artists File, 1986-2004 (Boxes 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, photographs, pamphlets, and notes regarding various artists, organized alphabetically by family name or stage name.
  - Afonichev, Vyacheslav, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Afrika (Sergei Bugaev), 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Badalov, Babi, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Bleikh, Galina, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Bogorad, Victor, 1997 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Elena Figurina, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 1: 6-7)
  - Gerasimenko, Valentin, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Gurevich, Alexandr, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Ivanova, Yulia, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Kaverzina, Marina, undated (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Koldobskaia, Marina, undated (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Koshelokhov, Boris, undated (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Kotel'nikov, Oleg, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Kovalsky, Sergey, 1987-1993 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Kolodzei, Natalya, 1990 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Manusov, Aleksandr, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Medvedev, Yuri, 1994 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Mikhailov, Vladimir, 1991 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Gruppa "Mit'ki,", 1990-2004 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Nikiforov, Yuri, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Nikitina, Lenina, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Novikov, Timur, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Orlov, Igor, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Orlov, Yevgeny, 1988 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Ovchinnikov, Vadim, 1993 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Rybakov, Yuly, 1988 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Savtcheko, Valentin, 1994 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Sazhin, Nikolai, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Shalabin, Valery, undated (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Marta and Slava, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Shinkarev, Vladimir, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Shmuilovich, Olga, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Schwartz, Solomon, undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Spivak, Marina, 1998 (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Tykotsky, Evgeny, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Ustiugov, Evgeny, undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Voinov, Vadim, undated (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Volkova, Marta, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 16)
    Also spelled Marta Wolkowa.
  - Zhigalov, Anatoly, 1991-2001 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Zhilina, Natalya, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Zhurkov, Igor, 1992 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Zubkov, Gennadi, 1997 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - List of artists of the Tovarishchestro Eksperimental'nogo Izobrazitel'go Isskustva (Fellowship for Experimental Fine Art), undated (Box-folder 3: 21)
- Personal Records, 1988-2001 (Boxes 4)
  Personal records of Barbara Hazard, including press coverage, clippings, brochures, and correspondence.
  - The Artists, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Mark Migdal, circa 1990s (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Notes on folder: "Émigré to California who organized a show for the Leningrad Artists, 1990-1991, and then refused to return the paintings" and "See also journals 1997, 1998, 1999."
  - Misha Yerish, 1997 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Regina and Anna: Manusova/Solevieva, Regina, undated (Box-folder 4: 4)
    Now in Houston, Texas with daughter, Anna Shparberg.
  - International Federation of Artists, 1992 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    One-time project to put on an international show in the St. Petersburg Manezh.
  - Pricelists, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Brochures, original, 1992-2001 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Brochures and announcements, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Russia clippings, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Press coverage, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Diaries, 1989-2008 (Boxes 5-6)
  Personal diaries of Barbara Hazard.
  - Elena and Valentin Visit #2, 1989 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Sergei Kovalaskii and Alyona visit, 1989 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Summer, 1989 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Prison uniform, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - April-June, 1990 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Diaries, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 5: 6-10)
  - Diaries, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 6: 1-6)
  - St. Petersburg, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 6: 7-8)
  - Diaries, 2003 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - St. Petersburg, 2004 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Summer 2004 email (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Alexander Manusov, 2004 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - St. Petersburg, 2005-2008 (Box-folder 6: 13-15)
  - Gallery exhibition pamphlet, 2002 (Box-folder 6: 16)
  - Aleksandr Manusov, book, 2001 (Box-folder 6: 17)
- Slides, undated (Box 7)
  Slides of artists' work, arranged alphabetically.
  - Index of artists' works (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - "Book 1" (Box-folder 7: 2-3)
  - "Book 2" (Box-folder 7: 4-6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 7: 7)
- Incremental Materials, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 8-10)
  The materials in the increment reflect Barbara Hazard’s own artwork and literary production, her interest in non-conformist work produced by artists in Leningrad/St. Petersburg, and encounters with artists during her trips to Russia.
  Archival material consists of Barbara Hazard’s correspondence, diary entries, drafts of part of her book Off Nevsky Prospect, published works, brochures and catalogs of her art exhibits, and miscellaneous related material. There are also photographs, slides, and negatives of Barbara Hazard and her own works and of experimental Russian artists from Leningrad/St. Petersburg and their work. Printed matter related to contemporary Russian art includes art magazines, exhibit brochures and announcements, exhibit catalogs (of individual exhibits and collective exhibits), and some books. Of note is a proposal by the “Free Culture” Humanitarian Foundation (St. Petersburg) to establish the St. Petersburg Museum of Non-Conformist Art.